IN THE GARDEN In each century since the beginning of the world wonderful things
have been discovered. In the last century more amazing things were found out than in any century
before. In this new century hundreds of things still more astounding will be
brought to light. At first people refuse to believe that a strange new thing can
be done, then they begin to hope it can be done, then they see it can be
done— —then it is done and all the world wonders why it was not done centuries
ago. One of the new things people began to find out in the last century was that
thoughts— —just mere thoughts— —are as powerful as electric batteries— —as good
for one as sunlight is, or as bad for one
as poison. To let a sad thought or a bad one get into your mind is as dangerous
as letting a scarlet fever germ get into your body. If you let it stay there after
it has got in you may never get over it as long as you
live. So long as Mistress Mary's mind was full of disagreeable thoughts about her
dislikes and sour opinions of people and her determination not to be pleased by
or interested in anything, she was a yellow-faced, sickly, bored and wretched
child. Circumstances, however, were very kind to her, though she was not at all
aware of it. They began to push her about for her own good. When her mind gradually
filled itself with robins, and Morland cottages crowded with children, with
queer crabbed old gardeners and common little Yorkshire housemaids, with
springtime and with secret gardens coming alive day by day, and also with a
more boy his "creatures," there was no room left for the disagreeable thoughts which
affected her liver and her digestion and made her yellow and
tired. So long as Colin shut himself up in his room and thought only of his
fears and weakness and his detestation of people who looked at him and
reflected hourly on humps and early death, he was a hysterical half crazy
little hypochondriac who knew nothing of the sunshine and the spring and also
also did not know that he could get well and could stand upon his feet if he
tried to do it. When new beautiful thoughts began to push out the old hideous
ones, life began to come back to him, his blood ran healthily through his veins
and strength poured into him like a flood. His scientific experiment was
quite practical and simple and there was nothing weird about it at all. Much more
surprising things can happen to anyone who, when a disagreeable or discouraged
thought comes into his mind, just has the sense to remember in time and push it
out by putting in an agreeable determinedly courageous one. Two things cannot be in one
place. "Where you Tender rose, my lad, A thistle cannot
grow." While the secret garden was coming alive and two children were coming alive with it,
there was a man wandering about certain far away beautiful places in the
Norwegian fjords and the valleys and mountains of Switzerland and he was a
man who for 10 years had kept his mind filled with dark and heartbroken
thinking. He had not been courageous; he had never tried to put any other
thoughts in the place of the dark ones.
He had wandered by blue lakes and thought them; he had laay on Mountain
sides with sheets of deep blue genin blooming all about him and flower
breaths filling all the air and he had thought them. A terrible sorrow had
fallen upon him when he had been happy and he had let his soul fill itself with
blackness and had refused obstinately to allow any rift of light to pierce
through. He had forgotten and deserted his home and his duties. When he traveled about, darkness
so brooded over him that the sight of him was a wrong done to other people
because it was as if he poisoned the air about him with
gloom. Most strangers thought he must be either half mad or a man with some
hidden crime on his soul. He was a tall man with a drawn face and crooked
shoulders and the name he always entered on hotel registers was archal Craven mle
Manor, Yorkshire, England." He had traveled far and wide since the day he saw Mistress Mary in
his study and told her she might have her "bit of earth." He had been in the most
beautiful places in Europe, though he had remained nowhere more than a few days. He
had chosen the quietest and remotest spots. He had been on the tops of
mountains whose heads were in the clouds s and had looked down on other mountains
when the sun rose and touched them with such light as made it seem as if the
world were just being born. But the light had never seemed to touch
himself until one day when he realized that for the first time in 10 years a
strange thing had happened. He was in a wonderful valley in the Austrian tyol and he had been
walking alone through such beauty as might have lifted any man's soul out of
shadow. He had walked a long way and it had not lifted his. But at last he had
felt tired and had thrown himself down to rest on a carpet of moss by a
stream. It was a clear little stream which ran quite merrily along on its
narrow way through the luscious damp greenness. Sometimes it made a sound
rather like very low laughter as it bubbled over and round
stones. He saw birds come and dip their heads to drink in it and then flick
their wings and fly away. It seemed like a thing alive and
yet its tiny voice made the stillness seem deeper. The valley was very, very
still. As he sat gazing into the clear running of the water archal Craven
gradually felt his mind and body both grow quiet, as quiet as the valley
itself. He wondered if he were going to sleep, but he was
not. He sat and gazed at the sunlit water and his eyes began to see things growing
at its edge. There was one lovely mass of blue Forget Me Nots growing so close to the
stream that its leaves were wet and at these he found himself looking as he
remembered he had looked at such things years ago.
He was actually thinking tenderly how lovely it was and what wonders of blue
its hundreds of little blossoms were. He did not know that just that simple
thought was slowly filling his mind— —filling and filling it until other
things were softly pushed aside. It was as if a sweet clear spring had begun to
rise in a stagnant pool and had risen and risen until at last it swept the
dark water away. But of course he did not think of this
himself. He only knew that the valley seemed to grow quieter and quieter as he
sat and stared at the bright delicate bless He did not know how long he sat
there or what was happening to him, but at last he moved as if he were awakening
and he got up slowly and stood on the moss carpet, drawing a long, deep, soft
breath and wondering at himself. Something seemed to have been unbound and released in him, very
quietly. "What is it?" he said, almost in a whisper, and he passed his hand over his
forehead. "I almost feel as if— —I were alive!" I do not know enough about the
wonderfulness of undiscovered things to be able to explain how this had happened
to him. Neither does anyone else yet.
He did not understand at all himself— —but he remembered this strange
hour months afterward when he was at mleth again and he found out quite by
accident that on this very day Colin had cried out as he went into the secret
garden: "I am going to live forever and ever and ever!" The singular calmness remained with
him the rest of the evening and he slept a new reposeful sleep; but it was not
with him very long. He did not know that it could be
kept. By the next night he had opened the doors wide to his dark thoughts and they
had come trooping and rushing back. He left the valley and went on his
wandering way again. But, strange as it seemed to him, there were minutes—
—sometimes half hours when, without his knowing why, the black burden seemed to
lift itself again and he knew he was a living man and not a dead one. Slowly—
—slowly— —for no reason that he knew of— —he was "coming alive" with the garden. As the
golden summer changed into the deeper golden autumn he went to the Lake of
ko There he found the loveliness of a dream. He spent his days upon the crystal
bless of the lake or he walked back into the soft thick verg of the hills and
tramped until he was tired so that he might sleep. But by this time he had begun to
sleep better, he knew, and his dreams had ceased to be a terror to him. "Perhaps," he
thought, "my body is growing stronger." It was growing stronger but—
—because of the rare peaceful hours when his thoughts were changed— —his soul was
slowly growing stronger, too. He began to think of mleth and wonder if he should not go
home. Now and then he wondered vaguely about his boy and asked himself what he
should feel when he went and stood by the carved for posted bed again and
looked down at the sharply chiseled Ivory white face while it slept and the
black lashes rimmed so startlingly the close shut eyes. He shrank from
it. One marvel of a day he had walked so far that when he returned the moon was
high and full and all the world was purple shadow and silver. The stillness
of lake and shore and wood was so wonderful that he did not go into the
villa he lived in. He walked down to a little bowered terrace at the water's
edge and sat upon a seat and breathed in all the heavenly sents of the night. He
felt the strange calmness stealing over him and it grew deeper and deeper until he fell asleep.
He did not know when he fell asleep and when he began to dream; his dream was so
real that he did not feel as if he were dreaming. He remembered afterward how
intensely wide awake and alert he had thought he was. He thought that as he sat and
breathed in the scent of the late roses and listened to the lapping of the water
at his feet he heard a voice calling. It was sweet and clear and happy and far
away. It seemed very far, but he heard it as distinctly as if it had been at his
very side. "Archie! Archie! Archie!" it said, and then again, sweeter and clearer than
before Archy Archie!" He thought he sprang to his feet not even
startled. It was such a real voice and it seemed so natural that he should hear it
lilus lilus he answered lilus where are you?"
"In the garden," it came back like a sound from a golden flute. "In the
garden!" And then the dream ended. But he did not awaken. He slept soundly and
sweetly all through the lovely night. When he did awake at last it was
brilliant morning and a servant was standing staring at him. He was an
Italian servant and was accustomed, as all the servants of the villa were,
to accepting without question any strange thing his foreign master might
do. No one ever knew when he would go out
or come in or where he would choose to sleep or if he would roam about the
garden or lie in the boat on the lake all night. The man held a Sala with some
letters on it and he waited quietly until Mr. Craven took
them. When he had gone away Mr. Craven sat a few moments holding them in his hand
and looking at the lake. His strange calm was still upon him and something more— —a
lightness as if the cruel thing which had been done had not happened as he
thought— —as if something had changed. He was remembering the dream— —the real— —real
dream. "In the garden!" he said, wondering at himself. "In the garden! But the door is
locked and the key is buried deep."
When he glanced at the letters a few minutes later he saw that the one lying
at the top of the rest was an English letter and came from
Yorkshire. It was directed in a plain woman's hand but it was not a hand he
knew. He opened it, scarcely thinking of the writer, but the first words attracted
his attention at once. Dear Sir: "I am Susan saby that made bold to speak to
you once on the more It was about Miss Mary I spoke. I will make bold to speak
again. Please, sir, I would come home if I was you. I think you would be glad to
come and— —if you will excuse me, sir— —I think your lady would ask you to come if
she was here. "Your obedient servant, Susan sby Mr. Craven read the letter twice
before he put it back in its envelope. He kept thinking about the
dream. "I will go back to mlit he said. "Yes, I'll go at
once." And he went through the garden to the villa and ordered Pitcher to prepare
for his return to England. In a few days he was in
Yorkshire again, and on his long railroad journey he found himself thinking of his
boy as he had never thought in all the 10 years past. During those years he had only
wished to forget him. Now, though he did not intend to think about him, memories of him
constantly drifted into his mind. He remembered the black days when
he had raved like a madman because the child was alive and the mother was dead.
He had refused to see it, and when he had
gone to look at it at last it had been such a weak wretched thing that everyone
had been sure it would die in a few days.
But to the surprise of those who took care of it the days passed and it lived
and then everyone believed it would be a deformed and crippled creature. He had
not meant to be a bad father, but he had not felt like a father at
all. He had supplied doctors and nurses and luxuries, but he had shrunk from the mere
thought of the boy and had buried himself in his own misery. The first time after a year's
absence he returned to mwe and the small miserable looking thing languidly and
indifferently lifted to his face the great gray eyes with black lashes around
them, so like and yet so horribly unlike the happy eyes he had adored, he could
not bear the sight of them and turned away pale as death. After that he scarcely ever saw
him except when he was asleep, and all he knew of him was that he was a confirmed
invalid, with a vicious, hysterical half insane temper. He could only be kept from
furies dangerous to himself by being given his own way in every
detail. All this was not an uplifting thing to recall, but as the train whirled
him through mountain passes and golden plains the man who was "coming alive"
began to think in a new way and he thought long and steadily and
deeply. "Perhaps I have been all wrong for 10 years," he said to himself 10 years is
a long time. It may be too late to do anything— —quite too late. What have I been
thinking of!" Of course this was the wrong Magic— —to begin by saying "too late." Even
Colin could have told him that. But he knew nothing of Magic— —either black or
white. This he had yet to learn. He wondered if Susan sby had taken courage
and written to him only because the motherly creature had realized that the
boy was much worse— —was fatally ill. If he had not been under the spell of the
curious calmness which had taken possession of him he would have been
more wretched than ever. But the calm had brought a sort of courage and hope with
it. Instead of giving way to thoughts of the worst he actually found he was
trying to believe in better things.
"Could it be possible that she sees that I may be able to do him good and control
him?" he thought. "I will go and see her on my way to
mlethwa But when on his way across the moall he stopped the carriage at the
cottage, seven or eight children who were playing about gathered in a group and
bobbing seven or eight friendly and polite curtsies told him that their
mother had gone to the other side of the moall early in the morning to help a
woman who had a new baby.
"Our Dickon," they volunteered, was over at the Manor working in one of the gardens
where he went several days each week. Mr.
Craven looked over the collection of sturdy little bodies and round red
cheeked faces, each one grinning in its own particular way, and he awoke to the
fact that they were a healthy likable lot. He smiled at their friendly grins
and took a golden sovereign from his pocket and gave it to "our Elizabeth Ellen" who was the
oldest. "If you divide that into eight parts there will be half a crown for
each of you," he said. Then amid grins and chuckles and bobbing of curtsies he drove away,
leaving ecstasy and nudging elbows and little jumps of joy behind. The drive across the
wonderfulness of the Moore was a soothing thing. Why did it seem to give
give him a sense of homecoming which he had been sure he could never feel again—
—that sense of the beauty of land and sky and purple bloom of distance and a
warming of the heart a drawing nearer to the great old house which had held those
of his blood for 600 years? How he had driven away from it the
last time, shuddering to think of its closed rooms and the boy lying in the
four-posted bed with the briaded hangings.
Was it possible that perhaps he might find him changed a little for the better
and that he might overcome his shrinking from him? How real that dream had been— —how
wonderful and clear the voice which called back to him, "In the garden— —In the
garden!" "I will try to find the key," he
said. "I will try to open the door. I must— —though I don't know
why." When he arrived at the Manor the servants who received him with the usual
ceremony noticed that he looked better and that he did not go to the remote
rooms where he usually lived attended by Pitcher. He went into the library and
sent for Mrs. Medlock. She came to him somewhat excited and curious and
flustered. "How is Master Colin, Medlock?" he inquired. "Well, sir," Mrs. Medlock answered,
"he's— —he's different, in a manner of spe speaking." "Worse?" he suggested. Mrs. Medlock
really was flushed. "Well, you see, sir," she tried to
explain, "neither Dr. Craven, nor the nurse, nor me can exactly make him out." "Why is
that?" "To tell the truth, sir, Master Colin might be better and he might be changing
for the worse. His appetite, sir, is past understanding— —and his ways—" "Has he become
more— —more peculiar?" her master asked, knitting his brows
anxiously. "That's it, sir. He's growing very peculiar— —when you compare him with
what he used to be. He used to eat nothing and then suddenly he began to eat something
enormous— —and then he stopped again all at once and the meals were sent back
just as they used to be. You never knew, sir, perhaps, that out of doors he never
would let himself be taken.
The things we've gone through to get him to go out in his chair would leave a
body trembling like a leaf. He'd throw himself into such a
state that Dr. Craven said he couldn't be responsible for forcing
him. Well, sir, just without warning— —not long after one of his worst tantrums he
suddenly insisted on being taken out every day by Miss Mary and Susan s's boy
Dickon that could push his chair. He took a fancy to both Miss Mary and and Dickon,
and Dickon brought his tame animals, and, if you'll credit it, sir, out of doors he
will stay from morning until night." "How does he look?" was the next
question. "If he took his food natural, sir, you'd think he was putting on flesh— —but
we're afraid it may be a sort of bloat.
He laughs sometimes in a queer way when he's alone with Miss Mary. He never used
to laugh at all.
Dr. Craven is coming to see you at once, if you'll allow him. He never was as
puzzled in his life." "Where is Master Colin now?" Mr. Craven
asked. "In the garden, sir. He's always in the garden— —though not a human creature
is allowed to go near for fear they'll look at him." Mr. Craven scarcely heard her
last words. "In the garden," he said, and after he had sent Mrs. Medlock away he
stood and repeated it again and again. "In the garden!" He had to make an effort to bring
himself back to the place he was standing in and when he felt he was on
earth again he turned and went out of the room. He took his way, as Mary had done,
through the door in the shrubbery and among the laurels and the fountain
beds. The fountain was playing now and was in circles by beds of brilliant autumn
flowers. He crossed the lawn and turned into the Long Walk by the iyed
walls. He did not walk quickly, but slowly, and his eyes were on the
path. He felt as if he were being drawn back to the place he had so long
forsaken, and he did not know why. As he drew near to it his step
became still more slow. He knew where the door was even though the ivy hung thick
over it— —but he did not know exactly where it lay— —that buried
key. So he stopped and stood still, looking about him, and almost the moment
after he had paused he started and listened— —asking himself if he were walking in a
dream. The ivy hung thick over the door, the key was buried under the shrubs, no
human being had passed that portal for 10 lonely years— —and yet inside the garden there were
sounds. They were the sounds of running scuffling feet seeming to chase round
and round under the trees, they were strange sounds of lowered suppressed
voices— —exclamations and smothered joyous cries. It seemed actually like the
laughter of young things, the uncontrollable laughter of children who
were trying not to be heard but who in in a moment or so— —as their excitement
mounted— —would burst forth. What in heaven's name was he
dreaming of— —what in heaven's name did he hear? Was he losing his reason and
thinking he heard things which were not for human ears? Was it that the far clear voice had
meant? And then the moment came, the uncontrollable moment when the sounds
forgot to hush themselves. The feet ran faster and faster— —they were nearing the
garden door— —there was quick strong young breathing and a wild outbreak of
laughing shouts which could not be contained— —and the door in the wall was
flung wide open, the sheet of ivy swinging back, and a boy burst through it
at full speed and, without seeing the outsider, dashed almost into his arms. Mr.
Craven had extended them just in time to save him from falling as result of his
unseeing dash against him, and when he held him away to look at him in
amazement at his being there he truly gasped for breath. He was a tall boy and
a handsome one. He was glowing with life and his running had sent splendid color
leaping to his face. He threw the thick hair back from his forehead and lifted a
pair of strange gray eyes— —eyes full of boyish laughter and rimmed with black
lashes like a fringe. It was the eyes which made Mr. Craven gasp for breath. "Who—
—What? Who!" he stammered. This was not what Colin had expected— —this was not what he
had planned. He had never thought of such a meeting. And yet to come dashing out—
—winning a race— —perhaps it was even better. He drew himself up to his very
tallest. Mary, who had been running with him and had dashed through the door too,
believed that he managed to make himself look taller than he had ever looked before— —inches
taller. "Father," he said, "I'm Colin. You can't believe it. I scarcely can myself.
I'm Colin." Like Mrs. Medlock, he did not understand what his father meant when he said
hurriedly: "In the garden! In the garden!" "Yes," hurried on Colin. "It was the
garden that did it— —and Mary and Dickon and the creatures— —and the Magic. No one
knows. We kept it to tell you when you
came. I'm well, I can beat Mary in a race.
I'm going to be an athlete." He said it all so like a healthy
boy— —his face flushed, his words tumbling over each other in his eagerness— —that Mr.
Craven's soul shook with unbelieving joy.
Colin put out his hand and laid it on his father's arm. "Aren't you glad, Father?" he ended.
"Aren't you glad? I'm going to live forever and ever
and ever!" Mr. Craven put his hands on both the boy's shoulders and held him still.
He knew he dared not even try to speak for a
moment. "Take me into the garden, my boy," he said at last. "And tell me all about
it." And so they led him in. The place was a wilderness of autumn gold and purple
and violet blue and flaming scarlet and on every side were sheaves of late L
standing together lies which were white or white and ruby. He remembered well when the first
of them had been planted that just at this season of the year their late
glories should reveal themselves. Late roses climbed and hung and clustered and
the sunshine deepening the hue of the yellowing trees made one feel that one
stood in an embowered temple of gold. The newcomer stood silent just as the
children had done when they came into its greyness He looked round and round. "I
thought it would be dead," he said. "Mary thought so at first," said Colin. "But it came
alive." Then they sat down under their tree— —all but Colin, who wanted to stand
while he told the story. It was the strangest thing he had ever heard
archeal Craven thought, as it was poured forth in headlong boy fashion. Mystery
and Magic and wild creatures, the weird midnight meeting— —the coming of the
spring— —the passion of insulted pride which had dragged the young rajer to his
feet to defy old Ben Weatherstaff to his face. The odd companionship, the play
acting, the great secret so carefully kept the The listener laughed until
tears came into his eyes and sometimes tears came into his eyes when he was not
laughing. The Athlete, the Lecturer, the Scientific Discoverer was a laughable,
lovable, healthy young human thing. "Now," he said at the end of the
story, "it need not be a secret anymore I dare say it will frighten them nearly
into fits when they see me— —but I am never going to get into the chair again.
I shall walk back with you, Father— —to the house." Ben weather staff's duties rarely
took him away from the gardens, but on this occasion he made an excuse to carry
some vegetables to the kitchen and being invited into the servants' hall by Mrs.
Medlock to drink a glass of beer he was
on the spot— —as he had hoped to be— —when the most dramatic event mleth Manor had
seen during the present generation actually took place.
One of the windows looking upon the courtyard gave also a glimpse of the
lawn. Mrs. Medlock, knowing Ben had come from the gardens, hoped that he might
have caught sight of his master and even by chance of his meeting with Master
Colin. "Did you see either of them we the staff she asked. Ben took his beer mug
from his mouth and wiped his lips with the back of his
hand I that I did," he answered with a shrewd significant air. "Both of them?"
suggested Mrs. Medlock. "Both of them returned Ben weather starf Thank you
kindly, ma'am, I could Su up another mug of it." "Together?" said Mrs. Medlock, hastily
overfilling his beer mug in her excitement. "Together, ma'am," and Ben gulped
down half of his new mug at one gulp. "Where was Master Colin? How did he
look? What did they say to each other?" "I didn't hear that," said Ben, "along
are only being on the step ladder looking over the wall. But I'll tell thee
this. There's been things going on outside as you house people knows now
about and what they'll find out they'll find out soon." And it was not 2 minutes before he
swallowed the last of his beer and waved his mug solemnly toward the window which
took in through the shrubbery a piece of the lawn.
"Look there," he said, "if that's curious.
Look what's coming across the grass." When Mrs. Medlock looked she threw
up her hands and gave a little shriek and every man and woman's servant within
hearing bolted across the servant's hall and stood looking through the window
with their eyes almost starting out of their heads. Across the lawn came the Master of mleth
and he looked as many of them had never seen him. And by his side with his head
up in the air and his eyes full of laughter walked as strongly and steadily
as any boy in Yorkshire— —Master Colin! THE
END thank you for listening to this story we hope you enjoyed it if you'd
like to hear more hit subscribe give us a thumbs up and share your thoughts in
the comments your support really motivates us to keep creating more audio